"Edible Skin Care—Sun Protection
from the Inside Out"
A Nature article
"Edible skin care"
underscored an opportunity
provided by
the skin's rapid turnover.
Our entire outer layer of skin
is completely regrown
every month
from the nutrients
we provide it,
so we are what we eat
not just years down the road,
but on a month-to-month basis.
For example, the amount
of vitamin C we eat
maps directly
onto the amount of vitamin C
we have in our skin.
Take skin frailty.
Skin atrophy with age
is not just a cosmetic issue.
It can result in skin tears,
bruising, itching.
A cross-sectional study
of dietary intake
and skin frailty
found that dietary patterns
characterized by higher
vegetable and fruit intake
were associated
with better skin condition.
To test the effects of greens,
Korean researchers
randomized women
to one of two doses
of chlorophyl
(equivalent to up
to a few tablespoons (29.60 ml)
of cooked spinach a day).
After three months,
skin biopsies showed
a significant increase
in collagen production,
accompanied by an increase
in skin elasticity
and a decrease
in facial wrinkles.
This may have been due in part
to an "inside-out"
sunscreen effect,
as less DNA damage was noted
after the same degree
of UV radiation.
Unfortunately, these were all
just comparisons to baseline,
as there was no control arm
included.
Still, this is the kind
of evidence cited
by dermatology journal
commentaries
with titles like "Eat Plenty
of Green Leafy Vegetables
for Photoprotection."
(Protection against the sun.)
There have been
placebo-controlled
randomized trials.
Compared to placebo,
ten months (but not five)
of an extract of curly kale
caused a significant improvement
in a noninvasive measure
of skin collagen status.
The researchers concluded
"a healthy lifestyle
including a diet
rich in carotenoids
is the best prevention strategy
against premature skin aging."
Randomized, double-blind,
placebo-controlled
clinical trials
also found apple extracts
can protect the skin
against the sun after 12 weeks,
as can a combination
of rosemary
and grapefruit extracts
after just 2 weeks,
though a blackcurrant
juice drink for 6 weeks
or a pomegranate extract
for 4 weeks did not.
What about whole foods?
Researchers burned
the butts of twenty women
with a UV lamp
before and after
half of them ate
three tablespoons (44.40 ml)
of tomato paste a day
for three months.
There was significantly less
DNA damage in the derrieres
of those who had been eating
the tomatoes,
as well as a reduction
in the collagen-eating enzyme
that plays a role in skin aging
activated by UV-induced
oxidative stress.
In mice, eating tomatoes
translates
into fewer UV-induced
skin cancers,
but no such long-term studies
have been performed in people.
DNA is damaged directly
by UV-B rays,
whereas the bulk
of UV radiation from the sun-
UV-A rays-damages DNA indirectly
by producing free radicals
that deplete the antioxidant
levels in our skin.
Dietary tomato paste protects
against UV-induced skin redness
in humans.
If we eat a lot
of anti-oxidant rich food,
such as tomato paste,
even just ten weeks before
swimsuit season (but not four),
we can reduce the redness
of a sunburn by 40 percent.
Eating grapes may also cut down
on UV-induced DNA damage
and inflammation.
It's like we have
built-in sunscreen in our skin.
Now, this isn't as good
as a high SPF sunblock,
and we shouldn't be sunbathing
in the first place,
but damage occurs every time
we are exposed to the sun
and much of that exposure
occurs
when our skin is
otherwise unprotected.
Just giving people supplements
containing the same amount
of the red pigment lycopene
failed to have
a significant effect,
suggesting it's
the constellation
of antioxidant constituents
in whole tomatoes
working together.
An excellent example
of this nutrient synergy
is the fact that even
mega-doses of vitamin C
or vitamin E alone
have no significant effect
on photoprotection
(skin defense against UV rays),
but when combined,
they increase
the UV radiation dose needed
to cause the same redness
by more than 75 percent.
See, antioxidants
often work together.
Vitamin C, for example,
regenerates vitamin E
once it becomes oxidized itself.
However, some carotenoids
can stand on their own.
Giving people the equivalent
of one to two daily servings
of dark green leafies' worth
of lutein and zeaxanthin
significantly improves
skin hydration, elasticity,
and photoprotection
starting within just two weeks.
Beta carotene works too.
A meta-analysis of seven
randomized controlled trials
found that a daily dose
as low as a cup (240 g)
of sweet potatoes' worth
protects your skin
from sunburn,
but it takes
a minimum of 10 weeks
to sufficiently build up
in your skin.
Skin biopsies also show
that diet-relevant doses
of beta-carotene can boost
collagen production four-fold
and decrease UV-induced
DNA damage by 30 percent,
combined with an improvement
in facial wrinkles
and skin elasticity
over a period of three months.
There was no control group,
though,
and a much larger, longer study
found that the same dose
of beta-carotene failed
to affect skin aging
over four years' time
compared to placebo.
A randomized, double-blind,
placebo-controlled trial
of coenzyme Q10
found it didn't provide
any UV protection,
but it was able to reduce
crow's feet wrinkles
by about 10 percent compared
to placebo within 12 weeks,
with no significant difference
reported
between groups getting
a low dose (50 milligrams a day)
or a high one
(150 milligrams a day).
Topical sunscreens
and dietary photoprotection
from foods like greens
and sweet potatoes
represent
complementary strategies
for safeguarding our skin.
Sunscreens have the advantage
of working almost immediately
and offering
much stronger shielding.
Produce protection builds up
slowly over weeks
and only achieves an SPF of 4,
compared to 10 to 40
or even higher sun protection
factor within
typical sunscreens.
On the other hand,
sunscreens have to be
deliberately applied
in sufficient amounts
and with sufficient coverage
(including
all the hard-to-reach places),
and then still can rub
or sweat off,
whereas the protection
from plants is ever-present
and built-in all over.
Combined, they naturally
complement each other.